A Register of the Jacques Benoist-Méchin Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jacques Benoist-Méchin Papers
1909-1994
2007C70
Jacques Benoist-Méchin
26 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (10.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Acquired in 2007, the Jacques Benoist-Méchin Papers represent a significant addition to the existing holdings in the Hoover Institution Archives relating to the collaborationist Vichy government in France during World War II. Although the papers are only part of the extant Benoit-Méchin materials in various depositories and private collections, the collection in the Hoover Institution Archives contains important documents from all major phases of Benoist-Méchin's multifaceted career as a literary figure, politician, and historian.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Chronology
1901 Born, Paris, France
1921 Served as interpreter, French occupation forces in the Ruhr, Germany
1925-1927 Director, Paris bureau, International News Service
1929-1930 Editor, l'Europe Nouvelle
1936 Author, Histoire de l'armée allemande (5 volumes) Joined pro-fascist party of Jacques Doriot, the Parti Populaire Français
1939 Author, Eclaircissements sur Mein Kampf d'Adolphe Hitler, le livre qui a changé la face du monde
1939 Mobilized into French army. Taken prisoner by German forces and interned in Voves, France
1940 Released from P.O.W. camp, and enters service of Vichy government of Philippe Pétain
1940-1942 Serves in various ministerial posts, under Darlan and Laval, in Vichy government
1944 Arrested as a collaborator after the Liberation of France and incarcerated
1947 Sentenced to death by French court. Death penalty is commuted to one of prison with hard labor
1947-1953 In prison, including in Fresnes, France. Released in an act of clemency by the government of Vincent Auriol
1954 Author, Mustapha Kemal
1956 Author, Soixante jours qui ébranlèrent l'occident: 10 mai—10 juillet 1940
1957-1976 Traveled widely as a journalist and author in the Middle East and North Africa, making the acquaintance of various Arab rulers. Served as an occasional private envoy of the French government in the same region
1959 Author, Un printemps arabe
1983 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Acquired in 2007, the Jacques Benoist-Méchin Papers represent a significant addition to the existing holdings in the Hoover Institution Archives relating to the collaborationist Vichy government in France during World War II. Although the papers are only part of the extant Benoit-Méchin materials in various depositories and private collectio ns, the collection in the Hoover Institution Archives contains important documents from all major phases of Benoist-Méchin's diverse careers as cultural figure, politician, and historian.
The papers will be of particular interest to historians of the Vichy period. The Speeches and Writings series shows Benoist-Méchin's evolution from cultivated litterateur to an ardently Germanophile historian and politician, one who enthusiastically embraced Nazi Germany's vision of a New Europe. Benoit-Méchin's writings also reveal his reinvention after World War II as an analyst and historian of Middle East and North African affairs.
The Vichy government file series includes a compilation of materials (called by Benoist-Méchin "notes politiques") that relate directly to his service, including a period as minister, in the Vichy regime. These document his work for Admiral François Darlan, his collaboration with the German ambassador to France, Otto Abetz, as well memoranda and reports, including an important letter sent to Philippe Pétain by Adolf Hitler to mark the first anniversary of France's surrender to Germany in 1940.
The Trial and imprisonment file series provides an intimate look at the judicial proceedings against Vichy collaborators and their subsequent experiences in prison. In this series, there is correspondence among Benoit-Méchin and his fellow prisoners, including Robert Brasilach in the period leading up to his execution. There are also art works in this file that depict prison life and the viewpoint of Vichy collaborators concerning the violence surrounding the liberation of France.
The extensive Correspondence series records Benoist-Méchin's enduring connections to collaborationist and ex-Nazi milieus in France, Germany, and elsewhere. Among these friends and acquaintances of Benoist-Méchin figure Fritz von Papen, Wolf Rüdiger Hess, Oswald and Diana Mosley, René de Chambrun, and Saint-Paulien (the pseudonym of Maurice-Ivan Sicard). There is also correspondence between Benoist-Méchin and French officials in the 1960s and 1970s, including Jacques Chirac and Georges Pompidou. Among other matters, these reveal Benoist-Méchin's behind-the-scenes role as an envoy of the French government to various Arab rulers in this period. The series also includes correspondence with some of these rulers, including Muamar Khadaffi (Muammar al-Gaddafi), who commissioned Benoist-Méchin to arrange the French publication of the Libyan leader's so-called Green Book. More materials on Benoist-Méchin's many travels and high-placed connections in the Arab world can be found in the Middle East and North Africa file series of the papers.
The extensive Photograph series contains hundreds of prints, many personally selected and arranged by Benoist-Méchin, that illustrate his career and what he considered to be its highlights, including his collaboration with the Nazis. There are some additional materials revealing of Benoist-Méchin's assessment of his wartime role in the Biographical file series.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 10 series: Biographical file, correspondence, speeches and writings, Vichy government file, Trial and imprisonment file, Middle East and North Africa file, subject file, writings by others, photographs, and oversize materials.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
National socialism.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1939-1945--Collaborationists.; Prisoners of war.; France--Politics and government--20th century.; France--Politics and government--1940-1945.; France--Foreign relations--Germany.; Germany--Foreign relations--France.; Germany--History, Military.; France--History--Occupation, 1940-1945.; Middle East--History.; Middle East--Politics and government.
Related Material
Gaston Bergery Papers, Hoover Institution Archives
René de Chambrun Papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Marcel Déat Papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Georges Scapini Papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Container List
- Biographical file, 1926-1982. (Box 1)
  Includes biography, clippings, legal records, memorandum, and scrapbook materials
  - Airline menus, undated (Folder 1: 1)
  - Biography covering Vichy period, undated. (Folder 1: 2)
    Typescript fragment
  - Clippings, 1941-1982 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Handbills and poster advertising speaking engagements, 1960-1961 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Legal records, including affidavits and correspondence
    - Libel case, 1964 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Request for amnesty, 1979 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Letter relating to refusal of Prix Goncourt, 1941 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Medical and military records, 1939-1940 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Memorandum from German military concerning a book by Benoist-Méchin, 1940 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Press credential, 1967 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Programs and ticket, 1934-1963 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Publisher's announcement, 1941 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Quotations from reviews of books by Benoist-Méchin, 1926-1978 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Scrapbook materials, 1934-1981. (Folder 1: 14)
    Includes commemorative circular relating to the thirtieth anniversary of the execution of Hermann Goering and other Nazi leaders, 1976
- Correspondence, 1919-1982.
  Contains cards, letters, and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - A, 1926-1979 (Folder 1: 15)
    - B, 1923-1980 (Folder 1: 16)
    - C, 1934-1982 (Folder 1: 17)
    - D, 1933-1973 (Folder 1: 18)
    - E, 1931-1981 (Folder 1: 19)
    - F, 1933-1977 (Folder 1: 20)
    - G, 1939-1981 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - H, 1939-1981 (Folder 2: 2)
    - I-J, 1934-1962 (Folder 2: 3)
    - K, 1938-1981 (Folder 2: 4)
    - L, 1924-1980 (Folder 2: 5)
    - M, 1931-1979 (Folder 2: 6)
    - N, 1932-1981 (Folder 2: 7)
    - O, 1959-1981 (Folder 2: 8)
    - P, 1938-1974 (Folder 2: 9)
    - R, 1929-1980 (Folder 2: 10)
    - S, 1932-1981 (Folder 2: 11)
    - T, 1932-1972 (Folder 2: 12)
    - U-V, 1956-1981 (Folder 2: 13)
    - W, 1941-1979 (Folder 2: 14)
    - X-Z, 1940-1964 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Unidentified
    - Undated (Folder 2: 16)
    - 1919-1939 (Folder 2: 17)
    - 1940s (Folder 2: 18)
    - 1950s (Folder 2: 19)
    - 1960-1981 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Abetz, Otto and Suzanne, 1938-1957 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Adam, Claude, 1981 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Adam, M., 1942 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Aguet, William, 1959-1962 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Albertani, Claude, undated (Folder 2: 25)
  - Albord, Tony, 1957-1965 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Ambassade de la république algérienne, 1976 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Amiguet, Philippe, 1934 (Folder 2: 28)
  - Arletty (stage name of Léonie Marie Julie Bathiat), Undated (Folder 2: 29)
  - Arnim, A. von, 1938 (Folder 2: 30)
  - Aron, Robert, 1927-1969 (Folder 2: 31)
  - Atabinen, Resit Saffet, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Auphan, Paul, Undated (Folder 3: 2)
  - Banet-Rivet, R., 1940 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Bardèche, Maurice, 1947-1977 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Barre, Raymond, 1957 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Baudoin, Paul, 1956-1963 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Beaumont, Etienne de, 1944 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Béguin, Albert, 1936-1937 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Benani, Ahmed, 1972 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Benoist-Méchin, La baronne (mother), 1940-1947 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Berenbrok, Hans Dieter, 1965 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Berger, Paul C., 1964 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Bergery, Gaston, undated (Folder 3: 13)
  - Billaud, Bernard, 1981 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Blaizot, Auguste, 1930-1933 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Bonnard, Abel, 1938-1958 (Folder 3: 16)
  - Bonnet, Georges, 1964-1966 (Folder 3: 17)
  - Bouzon, Raymond, 1957 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Breker, Arno, 1969-1981 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Briou, Marcel, Undated (Folder 3: 20)
  - British Broadcasting Corporation (Judith Bumpus), 1981-1982 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Calou, René, 1931-1932 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Cambon, Jules, 1932-1934 (Folder 3: 23)
  - Carbuccia, Horace de, 1943-1982 (Folder 3: 24)
  - Carton de Wiart, H., 1941-1942 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Chambrun, René de, 1959-1967 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Chamson, André, 1926-1929 (Folder 3: 27)
  - Chevalier, Jacques, 1960-1964 (Folder 3: 28)
  - Chiappe, Jean-François, 1978 (Folder 3: 29)
  - Chirac, Jacques, 1976-1979 (Folder 3: 30)
  - Ciry, Michel, 1972-1978 (Folder 3: 31)
  - Clary, Jean, 1942 (Folder 3: 32)
  - Clogenson, G., 1956-1957 (Folder 3: 33)
  - Cochin, Henry, 1924-1926 (Folder 3: 34)
  - Conquet, Alfred, 1956-1958 (Folder 3: 35)
  - Copeau, Jacques, 1941 (Folder 3: 36)
  - Corti, José, 1944 (Folder 3: 37)
  - Cossé-Brissac, Philippe de, 1943-1961 (Folder 3: 38)
  - Cousteau, J. P., 1973-1974 (Folder 3: 39)
  - Cousteau, Pierre Antoine, 1954 (Folder 3: 40)
  - Creely, Herbert, 1936-1938 (Folder 3: 41)
  - Daladier, Edouard, 1940 (Folder 3: 42)
  - Darlan, François, 1941 (Folder 3: 43)
  - Darnand, Jean-Philippe, 1957-1968 (Folder 3: 44)
  - Dautey, Pierre, 1964 (Folder 3: 45)
  - Dayet, René, 1955-1956 (Folder 3: 46)
  - Decortys, M., 1941-1942 (Folder 3: 47)
  - Dederer, Dr., 1938 (Folder 3: 48)
  - Delamarche, Léon, 1931 (Folder 3: 49)
  - Delettrez, J. M., 1966 (Folder 3: 50)
  - Dönitz, Karl, 1966 (Folder 3: 51)
  - Doré, Marcel, 1977 (Folder 3: 52)
  - Drieu la Rochelle, Pierre Eugène, undated (Folder 3: 53)
  - Du Bos, Charles, 1930-1934 (Folder 3: 54)
  - Dutourd, Jean, 1972-1979 (Folder 3: 55)
  - El Fekki, Ahmed Hassan, 1967 (Folder 3: 56)
  - Engel, Gerhard, 1965 (Folder 3: 57)
  - Fabre-Luce, Alfred, 1960-1967 (Folder 3: 58)
  - Falkenhausen, Cecile von, 1969 (Folder 3: 59)
  - Falkenhayn, Fritz von, undated (Folder 3: 60)
  - Faure, Edgar, 1964 (Folder 3: 61)
  - Faure, Paul, 1959 (Folder 3: 62)
  - Finet, Jacques, 1961 (Folder 3: 63)
  - Friedrich, Hubertus, 1981 (Folder 3: 64)
  - Gallais, B. le, 1961-1962 (Folder 3: 65)
  - Garrisson, Robert, 1979 (Folder 3: 66)
  - Germain, André, undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Ghéon, Henri, 1920 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Gibrat, R., 1956-1964 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Goetz, Philip Becker, 1927 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Gorand, Marguerite, 1958 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Grousset, René, 1944 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Grover, F. J., 1960-1979 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Guerard, J., 1956-1974 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Guermanova, Marie, undated (Folder 4: 9)
  - La Guilde du Livre, 1961 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Guillet, Louis, 1931 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Guth, Paul, 1979-1981 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Hachiya, Michihiko, 1956-1963 (Folder 4: 13)
  - Hammarskjöld, Dag, 1957 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Hanesse, (?), 1938 (Folder 4: 15)
  - Harcourt, François d', 1964-1966 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Harscouët, Raoul, 1942 (Folder 4: 17)
  - Hasquenoph, Marcel, 1963 (Folder 4: 18)
  - Haye, Henry, 1960-1964 (Folder 4: 19)
  - Haye, Paul, 1958 (Folder 4: 20)
  - Hennion, Horace, 1932 (Folder 4: 21)
  - Hentig, Werner Otto von, 1956-1964 (Folder 4: 22)
  - Héraud, Marcel, 1946-1956 (Folder 4: 23)
  - Hess, Wolf Rüdiger, 1966-1976 (Folder 4: 24)
  - Hofmann, Rudolph, 1961-1966 (Folder 4: 25)
  - Hubatsch, Walther, 1979 (Folder 4: 26)
  - Huxley, Aldous, 1932 (Folder 4: 27)
  - Imperial War Museum, 1940-1956 (Folder 4: 28)
  - Isorni, Jacques, 1945-1964 (Folder 4: 29)
  - Janet, Claude, 1964 (Folder 4: 30)
  - Jardin, Jean, 1951-1960 (Folder 4: 31)
  - Jonchay-Sonis, Christian du, 1971-1976 (Folder 4: 32)
  - Kadhafi, Muammar (Muammar al-Gaddafi), 1974-1975 (Folder 4: 33)
  - Kenderessy, Ernö, undated (Folder 4: 34)
  - Klein, Walter, 1947 (Folder 4: 35)
  - Kleist, Peter, 1963 (Folder 4: 36)
  - Kra, Suzanne, 1927 (Folder 4: 37)
  - Kreie, Werner, 1943 (Folder 4: 38)
  - Laborde, Jean de, 1960 (Folder 4: 39)
  - Laignoux, Bernard, circa 1947 (Folder 4: 40)
  - Laroche, Jane, 1965 (Folder 4: 41)
  - Laurencin, Marie, undated (Folder 4: 42)
  - Laval, Pierre, Madame, undated (Folder 4: 43)
  - Lawrence, Frieda, 1932 (Folder 4: 44)
  - Lebre, Henrique, 1955-1960 (Folder 4: 45)
  - Leers, Johann von (also known as Omar Amin), 1955 (Folder 4: 46)
  - Lehmann, Albert, undated (Folder 4: 47)
  - Lehman-Blaser, Ernst, 1952-1953 (Folder 4: 48)
  - Librairie Gallimard (Gaston Gallimard, Jean Paulhan), 1927-1934 (Folder 4: 49)
  - Lubin, Germaine, 1972-1974 (Folder 4: 50)
  - Ludin, Hanns, 1938-1939 (Folder 4: 51)
  - Lyautey, Pierre, 1964-1968 (Folder 4: 52)
  - Mabire, Jean, 1974-1975 (Folder 4: 53)
  - Manstein, Erich von, 1956-1967 (Folder 4: 54)
  - Mantzke, Martin, 1964-1965 (Folder 4: 55)
  - Marcel, Gabriel, undated (Folder 4: 56)
  - Marinetti, F. T., 1924 (Folder 4: 57)
  - Massena, A., 1964-1966 (Folder 4: 58)
  - McEvoy, Theodore N., 1957 (Folder 4: 59)
  - Meyer, Hellmuth, 1961-1977 (Folder 4: 60)
  - Mitterrand, François, circa 1981 (Folder 4: 61)
  - Monnier, Adrienne, 1921-1925 (Folder 4: 62)
  - Monzie, Albert de, 1934 (Folder 4: 63)
  - Morand, Hélène and Paul, 1950-1972 (Folder 4: 64)
  - Moreau, G., 1956 (Folder 4: 65)
  - Morozumi, Yoshihiko, 1979 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Mosley, Diana and Oswald, 1957-1965 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Mukherji, Savitri Devi, 1968-1971 (Folder 5: 3)
  - Mutaguchi, Yoshiro, 1965 (Folder 5: 4)
  - Nimier, Roger, 1965 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Naroun, A., 1966 (Folder 5: 6)
  - Nasser, Gamal Abdel, 1959-1961 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Ould Daddah, Moktar, 1971-1977 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Ould Menneya, Ahmed, 1971 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Papen, Franz von, 1955-1961 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Papon, Maurice, 1961 (Folder 5: 11)
  - Pappenheim, Rabe von, 1938-1966 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Paris, Henri, comte de, 1959-1980 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Paris-Presse (Pierre Charpy), 1961 (Folder 5: 14)
  - Pétain, Anne, 1956 (Folder 5: 15)
  - Pétain, Philippe, 1932-1942 (Folder 5: 16)
  - Petavit, Louis, 1952-1955 (Folder 5: 17)
  - Petiet, (?), General, 1957 (Folder 5: 18)
  - Petit-Gounelle, Jean-Claude, 1966 (Folder 5: 19)
  - Peyrefitte, Alain, 1964-1979 (Folder 5: 20)
  - Pinay, Antoine, 1961-1978 (Folder 5: 21)
  - Pirenne, Jacques, 1956 (Folder 5: 22)
  - Platón, Charles, 1942 (Folder 5: 23)
  - Pompidou, Georges, 1969-1974 (Folder 5: 24)
  - Poussas, Henri, 1922 (Folder 5: 25)
  - Pouzin, André, 1952-1974 (Folder 5: 26)
  - Prade, Georges, 1951-1961 (Folder 5: 27)
  - Rahn, Rudolf, 1964 (Folder 5: 28)
  - Raspail, Jean, 1974 (Folder 5: 29)
  - Rassinier, Paul, 1963 (Folder 5: 30)
  - Ratcliffe, Peter, 1959-1960 (Folder 5: 31)
  - Rebatet, Lucien and Véronique, 1947-1966 (Folder 5: 32)
  - Reininghaus, Dieter von, 1981 (Folder 5: 33)
  - Ribbentrop, Rudolf von, 1974 (Folder 5: 34)
  - Rivière, Jacques, 1920-1924 (Folder 5: 35)
  - Robin, M. de, 1942 (Folder 5: 36)
  - Rohan, K. A., 1963-1964 (Folder 5: 37)
  - Rolland, Romain, undated (Folder 5: 38)
  - Rossbach, Gerhard, 1966 (Folder 5: 39)
  - Rössler, Karl, 1940-1942 (Folder 5: 40)
  - Roux, Dominique de, 1960-1964 (Folder 5: 41)
  - Ryckmans, G., 1961-1962 (Folder 5: 42)
  - Saint-Paulien (Maurice-Ivan Sicard), 1962-1975 (Folder 5: 43)
  - Saint Simon, François de, 1955-1980 (Folder 5: 44)
  - Salan, Raoul, 1964-1966 (Folder 5: 45)
  - Schacht, Hjalmar, 1956-1957 (Folder 5: 46)
  - Schaumburg-Lippe, Friedrich Christian Prinz du, 1963-1968 (Folder 5: 47)
  - Schlumberger, Jean, 1923-1931 (Folder 5: 48)
  - Schmundt, Rudolf, 1942 (Folder 5: 49)
  - Schneider, Edouard, 1925-1926 (Folder 5: 50)
  - Senghor, Léopold Sédar, 1969 (Folder 5: 51)
  - Serrano Suñer, Ramón, 1942-1964 (Folder 5: 52)
  - Servan-Schreiber, Jean-Jacques, 1979 (Folder 5: 53)
  - Skorzeny, Otto, 1972-1974 (Folder 5: 54)
  - Soriano, Raphaël, 1961 (Folder 5: 55)
  - Soucy, Philippe de, 1941 (Folder 5: 56)
  - Speaight, Robert, 1935-1936 (Folder 5: 57)
  - Der Spiegel (Rudolf Augstein), 1969 (Folder 5: 58)
  - Supervielle, Jules, 1926 (Folder 5: 59)
  - Tournay, Raymond, 1949-1953 (Folder 5: 60)
  - Traz, Robert de, 1923 (Folder 5: 61)
  - Venohr, Wolfgang, 1979 (Folder 5: 62)
  - Vowinckel, Kurt, 1965-1969 (Folder 5: 63)
  - Warlimont, Walter, 1963-1967 (Folder 5: 64)
  - Weaver, M. L. H. L., undated (Folder 5: 65)
  - Weiss, Louise, 1927-1929 (Folder 5: 66)
  - Westphal, Siegfried, 1959 (Folder 5: 67)
  - Weygand, Maxime, 1932-1963 (Folder 5: 68)
  - Williamsen, C. A., 1964 (Folder 5: 69)
- Speeches and Writings, 1923-1994. (Box 6)
  Contains articles, monographs, and some unpublished writings, arranged chronologically
  - notes on Mozart., Undated (Folder 6: 1)
    Holograph
  - "Importance de Vincent d'Indy.", 1923 March (Folder 6: 2)
    Typescript
  - "Deutschlands neue Kriegswirtschaft.", Circa 1935 (Folder 6: 3)
  - "Journal de la Ferté-Hauterive.", 1940-1941 (Folder 6: 4)
  - "Adieu à un camarade de combat (Brasillach).", 1945 (Folder 6: 5)
  - "Darlan.", Circa 1946 (Folder 6: 6)
  - note concerning Benoist-Méchin's activities during World War II., Circa 1946 (Folder 6: 7)
  - "Conversations avec Filippo Anfuso.", 1946 (Folder 6: 8)
  - autobiographical meditation., Circa 1957 (Folder 6: 9)
  - "Riyadh au clair de lune.", Circa 1957 (Folder 6: 10)
  - Ibn-Séoud, 1957
    - Holograph and typescript fragments (Folder 6: 11)
    - Holograph and typescript appendices (Folder 6: 12)
  - account of a dinner in Nuremburg, West Germany., Circa 1960 (Folder 6: 13)
  - "Terre des agonies et des résurrections," Nouvelles de Turquie., 1962 November 30 (Folder 6: 14)
    Printed copy
  - Histoire de l'armée allemande, fourth edition, 1964
    - Holograph drafts, with some interpolated typescript pages
      - Table of contents (Folder 6: 15)
      - Map (Folder 6: 16)
      - Volume three (fragment) (Folder 6: 17)
      - Volume four (Folder 6: 18-20, Box-folder 7: 1-8)
      - Volume five (Folder 7: 9-10)
    - Proofs, with some interpolated holograph corrections and correspondence (Box 8)
      - Volume one (Folder 8: 1-8)
      - Volume one (Box-folder 9: 1-6)
      - Volume two (Folder 9: 7-8)
      - Volume two (Box-folder 10: 1-7)
      - Volume two (Box-folder 11: 1-8)
      - Volume two (Box-folder 12: 1-7)
      - Volume three (Folder 12: 8)
      - Volume three (Box-folder 13: 1-7)
      - Volume five (Folder 13: 8-9)
      - Volume five (Box-folder 14: 1-5)
      - Volume six (Folder 14: 6-8)
      - Volume six (Box-folder 15: 1-4)
  - "Ma rencontre avec Hitler," l'Histoire pour tous., 1965 March (Folder 15: 5)
  - "Sur une lettre de Manstein.", 1965 November (Folder 15: 6)
  - "Le barrage d'Assouan sautera-t-il?", 1967 March 15 (Folder 15: 7)
  - "La vérité sur le retour de l'Aiglon,"l'Aurore., 1969 July 24 (Folder 15: 8)
  - in collaboration with Jean Wolf, "Le monde arabe devant l'Europe d'hier et de demain.", Circa 1970 (Folder 15: 9)
  - lecture on the Arab world, Geneva, Switzerland., Circa 1970 (Folder 15: 10)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Les arabes et l'Europe.", Circa 1973 (Folder 15: 11)
  - Histoire des alaouites, 1994
    - Holograph
      - Part one (Folder 15: 12)
      - Part two (Folder 15: 13)
    - Typescript drafts (Box 16)
      - First (fragment) (Folder 16: 1)
      - Second (Folder 16: 2)
      - Third, including documentary annexes (Folder 16: 3-9)
- Vichy government file, 1940-1944. (Box 17)
  Contains aide-mémoire, correspondence, memorandum, and other materials compiled by Benoist-Méchin as "notes politiques", arranged by physical form
  - Aide-mémoire, 1941 (Folder 17: 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Brécard, Charles, 1942 (Folder 17: 2)
    - Darnand, Joseph, 1943 (Folder 17: 3)
    - Krug von Nidda, Roland, 1942 (Folder 17: 4)
    - Monzie, Anatole de, 1943 (Folder 17: 5)
    - Papen, Fritz von, 1942 (Folder 17: 6)
  - List of government expenses, 1944 (Folder 17: 7)
  - Memorandum from François Darlan, 1941 (Folder 17: 8)
  - "Notes politiques" compiled by Benoist-Méchin.
    Includes correspondence and memoranda
  - undated
    - 1941 (Folder 17: 9)
      - March-May (Folder 17: 10)
      - June (Folder 17: 11)
      - July (Folder 17: 12)
      - August (Folder 17: 13)
      - October (Folder 17: 14)
      - November (Folder 17: 15)
      - December
        - 1-17 (Folder 17: 16)
        - 18-30 (Folder 17: 17)
    - 1942
      - January-February (Folder 17: 18)
      - March (Folder 17: 19)
  - Reports, 1940 (Folder 17: 20)
- Trial and imprisonment file, 1935—1954. (Box 18)
  Contains art works, correspondence, legal and police records, medical records, printed matter, and writings by others, arranged by physical form
  - Art works, 1946-1947
    - Drawings by unknown artist, circa 1946 (Folder 18: 1)
    - Sketch of Benoist-Méchin, circa 1946 (Folder 18: 2)
    - Watercolors, 1946 and circa 1947 (Folder 18: 3)
  - Calendar, 1947 (Folder 18: 4)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1953
    - Unidentified, 1947-1953 (Folder 18: 5)
    - Aujol, Jean-Louis, 1947 (Folder 18: 6)